INSTRUCTOR: Hello, everyone,
and welcome to the content
video for machine
learning model comparison.
OK.
So this video is really
just a discussion
or sets up a discussion on
the different machine learning
models that exist.
What are they and why
are there so many?
Why isn't it just that
regression and all
the regression variations
can do the same thing
and we call it good with that?
And it compares what they do
and how they do it, essentially.
So as I mentioned,
there is a lot
of different machine
learning models out there
that fit data differently.
Each kind of have
algorithm on how
they fit that they pair
with that's different.
The structure of the
model itself is different
depending on the scenario.
And largely the reason we
have so many different models
is because we have so many
different types of data--
and not even just types
of data, but structure
of data where different
models perform better more
accurately on some data
sets rather than others.
And because of the vastness
of different types of data
in the world, all of these
machine learning models
do really, really
well in their space.
So let's go through a
quick example of that.
So you can see it here.
This gives a good
visual on what they do
and how they're different.
So the data set
I'm going to use,
I actually got it from sklearn.
And it's like a dummy
classification data set.
Really the visuals
are really good,
but the data is really simple.
And it's classification.
So classification refers to
you have multiple classes
and you're trying to
predict the correct one.
For example, it could be
an animal I'm predicting.
The data set could
be images and you're
predicting the difference
between cats and dogs
and hamsters and guinea pigs,
those would be the classes--
the dog class, cat class,
hamster class, guinea pig class.
And then you're trying to
learn which one is which
and then predict which
one is which in a new data
set you haven't seen yet.
This is much more simple.
It just uses data
points that can
be defined as the blue class
and then the red class.
And then it uses the most
popular, most successful machine
learning models of the day,
nearest neighbor, linear support
vector machine and other support
vector machine, Gaussian,
decision tree, random
forest, which by the way,
was developed by a
professor at Utah State
while she was doing her PhD
at Cal Berkeley, I believe.
And for those who
know Sherrod Jones,
Sherrod was her PhD student,
so he knows random forests
thoroughly.
Neural net AdaBoost,
naive Bayes.
So anyway, just a
slew of models here.
Then a really
simple data and then
we're going to predict the class
on each of those and take a look
and generate some
visuals on how it did.
All right.
So I run it.
And I don't need to say
too much about the code.
In case you're
curious, it just goes
through this kind of generic
data and learns on it,
fits it, and then
predicts it, and then
generates a visual to show that.
So let's go straight to the
visual, I think that'll help.
And it is big, so it
takes a second to load.
I'll see if I can fit the
whole thing on the page here.
Yeah, it might have been too big
that it-- oh no, there we go.
It made it.
Let me shrink it just a touch.
That looks good.
Let me go a little more.
OK, here we go.
All right.
So what are we looking at?
So the rows of the
data are each classes.
So the row is-- here's
the red and blue class
where you can see the red
class is all in the upper left,
the blue class kind
of makes a U here.
And that's the same all
the way across in the rows.
There we go.
And then the same
thing in the second row
here, the blue class
is all in the middle,
the red class is
all surrounding it.
That's the same
for the entire row.
And then each of the columns
is a different machine
learning model and how it
tried to classify that data.
And then same thing.
Third row is a different data
set, red and blue classes,
and each of the columns
is a different model.
OK, so here it is.
This is a really
good visual on--
it's the same data,
but each model,
it tries to separate
the classes differently.
Well, how does it do that?
Each model has an
associated algorithm
that it uses to fit the data.
Remember that the fitting
phase is the learning phase.
It's where we learn
about the data,
how the data is different,
how the classes are
different from each other.
And then the model tries to
segment or create class areas
that it can use to predict.
So here's nearest neighbor.
Nearest neighbor
you can see like--
compare it to human
intelligence for a second.
If I showed you this data on
the left here, these classes,
how would you draw a line
to divide those two areas?
Well, one line go through
there and call it good.
Well, you can see you're
similar to nearest
neighbors and neural net.
That's how the nearest neighbor
models and the neural net model
did it.
You can see-- look
at random forest.
It creates a tree.
But what does a tree do?
A tree creates a divide.
It says, all right, this
variable for these values
go to the left.
Remember the binary tree
that we talked about?
For this value of
input go to the left,
for this value go to the right.
It creates a divide.
Well, here in the image, you see
that divide by just these lines.
They create a section.
That section has
been divided off
because if it's in that
section, it will likely be--
let me give an
example, the red class.
So look at these lines right
here, this vertical line
and this horizontal line.
We've created a
section of the tree.
Well, this section, when
I make this visual here,
is for the red.
And then for these blues,
it tries to section off.
The real magic
comes in the middle
here where random forest is
really good at linearities
where it can come in here
and make little tiny sections
around the class.
That's really where you
get high accuracies.
Look at random
forest is 0.93 here.
That's the point.
Linear SVM is 0.88.
So trees, your eye can quickly
go to the tree-based models
by the lines where the
lines are sections you
know that's a tree-based model.
The ones that can
almost draw a circle,
check it out, like neural
net and naive Bayes,
those work really well when you
have these data sets right here.
And again, regression
handles linear data sets.
Well, the vast majority of--
the world grows in
ever infinite amounts
of data getting generated.
More and more of it
is not linear data.
It's data where inputs
have crazy random effects
on the outputs that
can't be drawn linearly.
So nonlinearities
in your data require
a nonlinear fitting
machine learning model.
And you can see here
the different ways
that machine learning
models will try and fit
the data so that they can
predict it most accurately.
This is a good visual.
I should also mention,
obviously, this video,
I'm talking about the
differences at a high level
here.
I'm not going to cover the
literals of how machine learning
models are constructed-- their
architecture, the algorithms
that fit are different.
However, that is very
interesting and very important
information.
I highly recommend you
take our courses here--
DATA 5600 and DATA 5610.
At least those are the names of
the classes at the time of this.
This video are extremely
good, extremely interesting.
And they take machine
learning from magic
to really the guts of what it
can do, how to take a problem
and put it into inputs and
outputs, inputs to be learned
and then an output
to predict, and when
to use which model in whatever
data scenario that you run into.
OK.
So that concludes this video
on machine learning models
and comparing how they work.
Thanks for watching.